<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true and perfecte description of a straunge monstar borne in the citty of Rome in Italy, in the yeare of our saluation. 1585 Vnder which is described both the originall and triumphant state of the Holy League, and also the sodain and desperate fall thereof in the yeare 1588. With certaine verses exhortatory to the King of Spayn, that hee would withdraw his persecuting hand from the Church of Christ. Wherein are also shewed some of the cruelties exercised vppon our countrey-men and others in the Inquisition and gallies of Spaine.</title>
            <author>I. L., fl. 1590.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1590</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 73 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04966</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15107</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106738</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842449</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842449</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7102</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04966)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7102)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 473:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true and perfecte description of a straunge monstar borne in the citty of Rome in Italy, in the yeare of our saluation. 1585 Vnder which is described both the originall and triumphant state of the Holy League, and also the sodain and desperate fall thereof in the yeare 1588. With certaine verses exhortatory to the King of Spayn, that hee would withdraw his persecuting hand from the Church of Christ. Wherein are also shewed some of the cruelties exercised vppon our countrey-men and others in the Inquisition and gallies of Spaine.</title>
                  <author>I. L., fl. 1590.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Wolfe for Walter Dight, and are to be sold by William Wright,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1590.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the courteous reader" signed: I.L.</note>
                  <note>In verse and prose.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through; some pages stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sainte Ligue (1576-1593) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Inquisition --  Spain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7102:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7102:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TRVE AND perfecte deſcription of a ſtraunge Monſtar borne in the Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Rome in Italy, in the yeare of our ſaluation. 1585.</p>
            <p>Vnder which is deſcribed both the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and triumphant ſtate of the Holy League, and alſo the ſodain and deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate fall thereof in the yeare 1588.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With certaine verſes exhortatory to the King of Spayn, that hee would withdraw his perſecuting hand from the Church of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein are alſo ſhewed ſome of the cruelties exerciſed vppon our countrey-men and others in the</hi> Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>and Gallies of Spaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON. <hi>Printed by Iohn Wolfe for Walter Dight, and are to be ſold by William Wright.</hi> 1590.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:7102:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7102:2"/>
            <head>To the courteous Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough moſte men may vnderſtand my purpoſe, in the deſcription of this monſter without farther decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, yet the Printer doubting leaſt it might ſeeme obſcure to ſome not well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted heretofore with the occaſions, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings of theſe preſet troubles in chriſtendom, at his requeſt I thought good to aduertiſe thus much. Firſt that the name of the Pope that now laſt tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nized was <hi>Sixtus Quintus</hi> or <hi>Sixtus,</hi> the fift of that name, who being by his ſeat <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt,</hi> (as other Popes his Predeceſſors were before him and by his ſex a man) yet I tearme him by the name of ſtrumpet,
<note place="margin">This prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy was litte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally fulfilled in the time of Pope Ioane, that was a wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table harlot.</note> harlot. &amp;c. as the beloued diſciple of our Sauiour doth in the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calips,</hi> call that man of Sinne, and agreable to that Scripture I bring the diuell in their confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, calling him the Queen of new Babilon (the place of his reſidence.) This Pope to ſhew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a moſt cruel ennemy to humane race, as moſt his predeceſſors haue been, though few in ſo high degree, being no ſooner ſeated in his bloudy ſeat, he ſtraight beates his braines, how to ſet al chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome together by the eares, partly through the pleaſure he taketh in ſhedding innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t bloud,
<pb facs="tcp:7102:3"/>partly to ſet himſelfe the ſurer in his <hi>Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> chaire, (now almoſt rotten) and wholly to extinguiſh and roote out the glorious and moſte comfortable Goſpell of our Sauiour, with all the profeſſors thereof, that hee might ſo bring it to paſse, that their might be no memorie remaining of the one nor the other. And becauſe the diuell is alwaies ready at our elbowe to pricke vs for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, as ſoone as we haue conceiued any euill in our harts, and ſo much the readier, by how much the conceiued miſchief is the greater. So no doubt this Pope, whoſe conceit being againſt Chriſt &amp; his members, I acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt the chiefeſt of al ſins, what ſo euer, had no ſooner laid the plot of his vnſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble miſchief in his hart, but the diuil was as dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to vrge him to put it in as ſpedy practiſe. And therefore Iſay this monſter or bloudy league, to be begotten of the diuel vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the forenamed whor of Rome, as who ſo loketh wel into the nature of the ſaid Holy league, muſt needes ſay with mee, that Hel it ſelf was of cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſail to the eſtabliſhing thereof. I tearme it vntimely birth, in reſpect of the ſtrumpets eagernes in bringing it forth, for ſhe brought forth her miſhapen creature after her comming to the Popedome, in halfe the time
<pb facs="tcp:7102:3"/>that women commonly vſe to go with child, euen within the compas of four moneths: yet the bug ſhewed not himſelfe in his iollity till the year <hi>88.</hi> the cauſe wherof liudge to be a certain propheſy inuented amongſt the Papiſts, that in the ſaide yeare of <hi>88.</hi> there ſhould be but one king, one pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor and one flocke, the interpretation whereof they apply, the King, to be Phillip of Spayn, the pastor to be the Pope, and the flocke to be al peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and nations of our Europe, which in that year ſhould all be thrall and ſlaues to that king &amp; pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor. Yet note by the way, friendly Reader, that this great paſtor, that wold haue ſo great a flock or rather the fleece and fel of them, &amp; that now vanteth to excell all kings, as much as the Sunne excelleth the Moone, was of late a begging gray fryer,
<note place="margin">The Franciſea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Friers when they begge at the dore, they aſke it for and in the name of Saint Francis himſelfe.</note> going fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dore to dore with a wallet on his backe, begging bread for S. Frauncis, but that begging eſtate he hath as clean forgotten now, as though his feete now cladde with purple veluet ſhoes, had neuer gone bare foote.</p>
            <p>The king of Spayn, ſo inriched by his weſt <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia Mines</hi> &amp; his reuenews ſo increaſed through his late vſurping of Portingall, and thereby alſo the eaſt <hi>India,</hi> being the chief piller of the Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb facs="tcp:7102:4"/>and without whom it could neuer haue ſtoode ſo long, I place him for the monſters right arme, in whome the Pope puts all his confidence, they two hang together as the pennard and inck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horne, the Pope giues the king many buls, which yeelds great profite to his coffers, therefore the king is his cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pion and generall in al his battails, yet note, thoſe fat buls come not out of the Popes medowes, he giues him but a pig of his owne ſow, the Popes gift is but yearly a ſheete of paper, but all the profite that comes to the king, comes from his ſubiects purſes, and ſo drunken is this king becom with the winelees of this harlots golde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cup that he cannot diſcern it. The late duke of Guiſe ſometime, in reſpect of his bloudy mind, the fitteſt man in our Europe, to haue a principall place a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Popes own children, he being co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cald the Popes butcher, is plaſte as the mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters left arm which arme a long time was great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly feared of al men, til it pleaſed the Lord to ſett his church free from ſo cruel a ſcourge. I deſcribe the monſtar firſt, as he was in his greatest pride, but after according to his preſent picture, I deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribe him as he lately was. I doubt not but the reſt may be well vnderſtoode. Farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>He that wiſheth ſpeedy conuertion or haſty confuſion to the Monſter. I. L.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:7102:4"/>
            <head>The deſcription of the Monſter.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Ope Sixtus,</hi> one of the moſt ſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſtrumpets of all her whooriſh predeceſſors, beginning her raigne in the yeare of our ſaluation <hi>1585,</hi> and ſéeing her dignitie and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes ſo farre inferiour to moſt Popes in time paſt,
<note place="margin">In times paſt the Popes had great fees out of all kingdomes in Europe, and this fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke Sixtus had nothing but out of Spaine, Italy, and partes of Germany, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> woonder not that he fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed like one ſtark madde.</note> beganne to growe ſo malancholie, that ſhee wanted little fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> falling into an incurable frenzie: ſtraight ſhe ſets all her wits abroach, laying ſundry plots for the repayring of the decayed dignitie of the ſometime flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing chayre. The Diuell a diligent attendant on any ſexe poſſeſſed with like cogitation, appeared vnto her in ſhape fitteſt to pleaſe the humour of ſo common a curtizan, and ſaluting her farre vnlike the churliſh courteſie of his infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Countrey, he gins reuiue her out of the dumpe with theſe friendly ſpéeches. How now braue Ladie (quoth he) what, all in your dumpes? Is this a moode beſéeming the Quéene of new Babylon? Is this the countenance of her that ſhould make all Nations of the earth drunke in her beautie, and bewitcht by her brauerie? May the Kinges of the earth (whom thou muſt allure to loue thée) like of a melancholly Ladie? Hath Fortune firſt called thée from a ruſſet coole to a red hatt, and from that hatte to a tripled Crowne, and ſhouldeſt thou not knowe how to vſe For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune that ſtandes wholy at thy becke? Or haue euer I ſayled thée at the pinch, that thou ſhouldſt any thing doubt now of my readineſſe at néede? Nay frollike fayre Quéene and plucke vp your ſpirites: let not this ſucceſſiue ſeate fall farther to decay in you, that whylome ſo flouriſhed by your moſt famous foregoers: in ſharpeneſſe of wit fewe of them euer came uéere you, and in pollicie who euer was
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:7102:5"/>comparable? They haue by degrées loſt of late euery one a ſhare, ſo that the famous chayre is become to the ſtate as nowe to our gréefes we ſée it in: how befitting will it then be for braue <hi>Sixtus</hi> to imploy her ſelfe, not onely to recouer that alreadie loſt, but alſo in ſubduing that which as yet hath little bowed vnder any of their banners. Shall you who by the helpe of that mightie Monarch of Spaine, together with your owne induſtrie,
<note place="margin">The King of Spaine hath his voyce in the Popes election, and beareth grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſway of all other voyces.</note> came to this haughtie ſeate, ſéeme to want eyther friends or pollicy, not onely to maintain it, but againe to lift it eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the clouds? Caſt off theſe dumpes (my loue) for ſhame, and practiſe without doubting to performe what ſo euer you enterpriſe. Doe you forget that it was at firſt a hundred times more diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult to eſtabliſh this chaire, when yet it was not, then it is now to maintaine it, hauing ſuch helpes? Are the coffers ſo ſtuft to others, become ſo bare and emptie to thée? Let par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons purchaſe golde, and ſale of Bulles ſupply that want, rayſe the price of thy pardons, and force men vppon payne of fire to take thy Buls, haſt thou not aſword as well as the keyes of Heauen? If men grow careleſſe of thy par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons, pardonne them perforce. Be of good cheare braue Quéene and let diſpayre be farre from thée, vſe my aduiſe and doubt not all ſhall be well. Her holineſſe ſtarting vppe as from a ſlumber, and doubting leaſt ſhee dreampt, that which afterwardes ſhe perceiued more plaine to be the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſpéeches of her ſwéete heart in déede: after ſome louing imbraſinges, ſhe burſt foorth into this heauie reply. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell not my beſt beloued, and neuer fayling friend at néede, that you finde me driuen into this preſent dumpe, out of which your comfortable ſpéech and preſence hath euen now ſet me frée. Our ſeate, ſometime as you know the onely woonder of the world for brauerie and pompe, hauing euer ſince the preaching of that accurſed Germayne <hi>Luther</hi> and his ſchollers daily diminiſhed in dignitie, I find at my firſt entrie ſo vnlike to that it hath béene within the compaſſe of my owne remembrance, that our Monarchie ſéemes nowe ſcant a Molehill, to that it was woont to be in the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:7102:5"/>time of ſome of our more then happy predeceſſors, ſelfe eaſe ſo poſſeſſing our latter Popes, that euery one hath loſt his little, for ſturring ſo little to ſtoppe the ſoare at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: and by regarding too too litle the pompe and eaſe of vs their ſucceſſor, I finde to my woe, this preſent ſeat ſo weake, that vnleſſe I beſturre mée better then they haue donne: I ſée no remedie but ſeat and ſucceſſion will ende both in me. Thus ſéeing (right truſtie friend) this great charge as well for our ſelfe as our ſucceſſors, depending wholy vpon our owne ſhoulders, woonder not to ſée me ſo diſquieted at the heart and vexed in mind, till I haue found ſome way how to repaire this our ouerruinated ſeat. That which at the firſt might haue béene ſtopt with a little and ſmall charge, nowe by running ſo long vnſtayed will coſt millions and a whole Ocean of bloud: the effuſion of bloud is our leaſt care, but want of thoſe millions ſtickes in our ſtomacke. Spaine, the Princes and Senioryes of Italy, the Biſhoppricke of Colen, with fewe others remaine firme vnto vs, when as the reſt of Europe is eyther fallen quite from vs, or at leaſt ſo wauering, that in moſt néede we are likeſt to be deceiued by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. If the Emperie ſhould change from the houſe of Auſtria (as it is to be feared) and ſo fall to ſome of our profeſſed enemies,
<note place="margin">He meaneth the king of Nauarre, now to the Popes griefe, the French king: whom the League ſo purſueth: but God is his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. Here the Pope doubts not in vaine, for ſince this parlee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene him and the diuel, the Pola<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders haue elected the valiant Prince Signiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mundus, ſon to the king of Sweden, a Proteſtant. Here for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce I muſt let paſſe the filthy railing ſpeeches, that the quondam ruſſer hooded Sixtus vomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth out of his ſtinking mouth, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our Princeſſe, whome God long preſerue in deſpite of all her foes, for they are ſuch as are not for any good ſubiect to write, nor for any chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian care to brooke the hearing. The diſcredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the Popes pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s is no ſmall hinderance to her Holines.</note> what a blow were that to light on our ouerburthened ſhoulders. France for want of iſſue, hath for next ſucceſſor * him that our heart moſt abhorreth, againſt whome wée haue ſent foorth our curſes and Buls, but he eſtéemes them all as bubbles and ſpéedes the better by how much the more he hath béene excommunicated and curſt.</p>
            <p>Poland that brooketh no ſucceſſour by iſſue, by electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I feare, may admit ſome Lutheran, and then all hope of ſuccor from thence were cleane cut off. The Ruſſies and Muſcouites, howbeit they maintaine ſome of our ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, yet how ſlenderly they accompt of vs, it is al too wel knowne, and how ſoone they will quite reiect vs, who can tell? And in the meane time, what by the farre diſtance of the way, and by the little reſpect they haue vnto vs, wée
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:7102:6"/>haue no cauſe to truſt to their aide. England, whom with her Quéene, our predeceſſors haue ſo long and déepely cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that there hath bin no malediction againſt her and hirs left vnpronounced, flouriſheth nowe more then euer, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath <hi>Pius Quintus</hi> and Gregorie, both of famous me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie, notwitſtanding all their coſts and charges, bin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to hatch ſo many Engliſh Seminaries, to infect that Countrie: but thoſe Vniuerſities of Cambridge and Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forde, ſo vnhappily for vs, maintained by that accurſed Quéene, haue ſent forth ſuch an innumerable rable of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, that not onely our Engliſh Seminaries, but all our learned Ieſuites of all nations are ſo put to ſilence by their preachings and writings, that they haue not a word to ſay more in my quarrell: well they may brabble, but thoſe biſhops and miniſters of England ſo beate them with their anſweres, that they are almoſt beaten dumbe. And yet our Engliſh Seminaries haue waded further in our cauſe then any other Writers heretofore. And as for our pardons they are alſo growen ſo farre out of credit by the Writings and Sermons of Engliſh and other Miniſters, which ſtill teach men where they may haue pardons gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, and onely for aſking, that now there is ſuch running to Chriſt for Indulgences, and plenarie remiſſion that not one amongſt twentie comes to me his vicar. Euery ſowter is now growen ſo malapert, that he preſumeth at the firſt iumpe to ruſh euen to Chriſt himſelfe, without aſking leaue of one or an other Saint in Heauen or Hell.
<note place="margin">Note that all Saints are not in heauen, for the pope hath canonized ſuch a nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of traitors, that hell is not vnfurnis ſhed of ſaintes ſuch as they be.</note> And this is the good that we get alſo, in that the Scripture is in ſo many vulgare tongues, for becauſe Chriſt ſaith with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exception, Come vnto me all ye that labour and are heauie laden &amp;c. Euery Tinkar that is touched with a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle repentance, now by vnderſtanding the Scriptures, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it to be ſpoken alſo vnto him, and ſo at the firſt daſh runnes boldely to Chriſt, without offering one peny vnto me his porter, or to any other of his courte for his admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. What hope reſteth then in my bulles or pardons? Thus leauing to ſpeake of many others that are almoſt as
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:7102:6"/>ſharpe thornes vnto our ſides, as the Quéene of England is. By this little I haue ſaide, I know thou canſt come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of the reſt, and ſo well waying the cares that vexe vs, togither with the tickliſh ſtate of our tottering chaire, ceaſe to blame me for ſitting ſo malecontent as lately you found me.</p>
            <p>The Diuell that heard nothing all this while, but that he too well knew before, cuts off this concubines dolefull tale with a louing kiſſe. Peace, faire Quéene, quoth hée, and adde no further oyle ta my flame, thou renueſt my ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes without telling mée any newes: Thou knoweſt to my power, I haue ayded the Sorcerers, Coniurers, and Inchanters of thy predeceſſors againſt our capitall enemie of England all that I might. But he whoſe name I trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to rehearſe, hath put ſuch a hooke in my noſtrelles, that I can goe no further then he lets me looſe, it is in his hand to reſtraine my rage, and to giue me libertie to execute his wrath when he ſéeth time: but whuſht, be ſtill, ſéeing thy ſorcerers by me, nor I by them can do no more then lifteth him that ruleth vs all, we muſt caſt about, and bring the other tacke aboorde, wée muſt rake all the corners of hell for a new deuice, ſéeing all our former practiſes faile vs, we will prouide a remedy for all, and all ſhall be to our content Lady I warrant thée. With that togither they goe into hir holines priuy chamber, where they laid their heads to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither. But what they did, or how they handled the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, I know not, but hir holines beganne to looke big, and waxe big, as though the Diuelles and ſhe had made worke for the Beodles of Bridewell, and in leſſe ſpace by fiue mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths at leaſt, then ordinary courſe, hir holines was deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of hir vntimely birth: yet the childe being aliue, the tender care of the mother ſo foſtred and brought it vp, that inſmall time it wared very ſtrong, yea, the monſter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came ſo mightie in ſo little ſpace, that moſt Kinges of the earth ſtoode at the gaze, expecting with feare the euent of his power. While the dadde and damme beganne to rub the elbowe for ioy, and their hearts dauncing within them,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:7102:7"/>ſaying one to another, This is he ſhall remedie all, and he ſhall aduance our ſeat higher by a degrée then euer it was: the damme ſung lullabie, and the dadde rockt the cradle, ſo long, till neyther Rome, the cradle, nor all Italie could lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger containe him, for the ſtripling woulde abroad to ſearch out aduentures: And therefore I will firſt ſhewe you his ſhape, as he was in his greateſt pride. He had two heads, the one altogither like the ſire, and the other like the da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me, which heads ſpake prowd blaſphemies againſt heauen, and the ruler therof, their lookes loftie, euen like the ſonne of pride and ſinne, terrible like the ſéede of Serpents, and fierce like the red dragon.</p>
            <p>From his right ſhoulder in ſteade of an arme, grewe out a mighty Prince with a crowne imperiall on his head, to looke to, full of all pompe and maieſtie, ſéeming at the view by his rich ſhew to be ſole commander of all the golde mines in the world, he had a ſword in his hand more braue to looke to, then fearefull by any ſigne of manly ſtrokes gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen therewith,
<note place="margin">The king of Spaine his late vſurping of Portingale, poſſeſſeth alſo all ſuch partes of the Eaſt India as ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt belonged to Portingale.</note> the ſcabbard moſt richly beſet with ſtone and pearle, as though the Eaſt India had lately become his ſlaue: he cried out in the Spaniſh tongue, ſo lowde, that not onely all Europe, but alſo great parte of Affrica trembled at the prowd noiſe, <hi>El mundo no me baſta:</hi> which his ſpéech I take to be thus much in Engliſh, <hi>The world ſufficeth me not.</hi> From his left ſhoulder procéeded alſo in place of the other arme, a prince to looke on very grimme, and ſterne, with a coronet on his head, his armes thorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imbrued in blood, his ſworde died red in the ſame, as though he had lately come from the ſlaughter of an infinite number of ſéely lambes and ſhéepe: his ſparkling eies ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med all inraged in ire, his browe frowning nothing to the ſhewe but gaſtly death. In fine, he ſéemed wholie a hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh fury, prowdly roaring out in the French tongue this horrible ſpéech, <hi>En despit du Ciel.</hi> which I vnderſtande thus in Engliſh, <hi>In despite of heauen.</hi> His body contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the place of heart, lyuer, lungs, guttes, gall, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther entralles, a number of fat friars of all orders, prieſtes,
<pb facs="tcp:7102:7"/>monkes and Ieſuites, ſome laying their heads together, as debating matter of great moment, ſome ſinging, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers faring as merry as Crickets, the potte with <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>inum theologicum,</hi> in the meane while hauing little reſt, but ſtil walking from mouth to mouth, and toſſed like a teniſe bal, from hand to hand, as though they purpoſely meante to make themſelues leane for the kingdome of heauen: there was in fine ſuch a confuſed noiſe amongeſt them, of all the languages in our Europe, that with much adooe I coulde heare diſtinctly any of their ſeuerall ſpéeches, yet liſtening attentiuely to the Engliſh, which by meanes of the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of other languages was hardly diſcerned, I heard one cry flatly, <hi>Neuer ſuch cauſe of ioy.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Be like it was ſome Engliſh Ieſuite that hoped ſhortly to become a Cardinall in England.</note>
            </p>
            <p>His taile was double like his necke, from which ſproong out many madde heads, ſome ſéeming noble, many of good birth, but moſt, the ſcumme and outcaſt of the world, ready at an houres warning to ſerue the Diuell himſelfe for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney: all theſe well armed, and as it were, ready at a pinch to ſtrike without reſpect of age or ſexe: the Monſter ſéem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not greatlie troubled in drawing them, by meanes of their great willingnes, to followe of their owne accorde: their noiſe was no leſſe confuſed then that of the belly-gods before mentioned, ſaue that I heard not a worde of Engliſh amongſt them, to my remembrance, but I heard an Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian ſomewhat louder then the reſt, all in a brauerie, and in the hoigh to ſay, <hi>Hor, ò mai, ricco,</hi> which I take to be thus much in Engliſh, <hi>Rich now or neuer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Downe from his bréech on the right ſide ſtoode in ſteade of a legge, a Cardinall, prowde in his geſture, ſéeming to ſupporte his ſhare of the great burthen, as though hee had ſcant ſuſtained a fether, a braue luſtie fellowe, princelike in countenance, caſting a ſmirking looke from a wanton rol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling eie, as though a window in Rome ſhould ſcant eſcape his piercing ſight, and in a pleaſant vaine I heard hym vtter in Latine, <hi>Quis non portabit ſpe?</hi> which I thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrue, Who would not beare on hope?</p>
            <p>On the other ſide, in ſteade of the monſters lefte legge
<pb facs="tcp:7102:8"/>ſtood, a no leſſe frolike mitred Biſhop, fat and better fedde by oddes then the Cardinall, his belly ſtrouting out, as though it contained the better parte of a barrel of Reniſhe wine, wholy deſpiſing the cares of this worlde, as dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting himſelfe altogether to <hi>Tempus bonum,</hi> yet ſéeming to hope of farther preferment and eaſe, I heard him ſay thus in latine, <hi>Fero vt quieſcam,</hi> meaning this, I beare nowe for after eaſe.</p>
            <p>This Monſter, in the ſhape preſcribed, beeing then in his ruffe and greateſt iollitie, put the worlde in ſuch a maze that it was ſtrange to heare euery ſeuerall mans opinion, eſpecially when her holines (that diſpoſeth of Baptiſme at her pleaſure) vouchſafed to baptiſe her childe with the name of <hi>Holy-League:</hi> then, how many men, ſo manie mindes, ſome ſayde they neuer ſawe ſo vgly a ſhape vnder ſo reuerent a name, ſome ſayde the name and the perſon agréed as well as (kill Bull) for a gentle womans little fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting hound, that might be put in her gloue: others thought the better of the beaſt, for the reſpect of the name, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny were ſo madde as to thinke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Monſtar with the name, to be both from aboue, ſo were the multitude bewitched and wiſe men ledde into error: But all men that lookt nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly into the proportion and force of euery limme, ſtoode more affrayde of his might then amazed at his ſhape: whether he was firſt to take his progreſſe, few men knew but euery man feared, for euerie one doubted his owne home: the greateſt rumors went, that he would beginne firſt with France, Flanders, and Englande: yet Affrica doubting leaſt he would take Barbarie in his waye liſted not to be vnprouided for his entertaynement, neyther ment Aſia to ſléepe in ſecuritie:
<note place="margin">The names of kings of the Weſt India, who at thys preſent with all their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectes liue in moſte miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble bondage vnder the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards, and haue ſo done a long time, enduring more torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts then may bee well named, in ſo muche that they are perſwaded, that the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niardes are a people aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded out of hel for their ſins.</note> a horrible Monſter (ſaye you) ſo to ſcare the thrée corners of the worlde: but had America béene alſo in peace, where to haue viewed him to the full, I doubt not but her prowdeſt * Caſſiques would haue trembled at the ſight: &amp; ſo much the ſooner, becauſe the right arme ſpoke in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Spaniſh tongue ſuch terrible things, in which language the Weſt India, (contayned in Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rica)
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:7102:8"/>ſuffered ſuch proud threates, and therewithall ſuch intollerable tormentes, that the poore Indians thinke ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily that there is no other language vſed in Hell among the diuels. But leauing thoſe miſerable Indians in their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie and perpetuall ſlauerie, where they are conſtrayned dayly to heare the thrée throated Cerberus, barking out nothing but horror in the ſaid language. This Monſter hath begunne his ſtately march, and gone quite thorough Fraunce and Flanders, where in Fraunce with his lefte arme he did horrible things, the right arme afflicting Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders with vnſpeakeable miſeries, and in the yeare 1588. being then in his full ſtrength, who can declare the haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie wordes he threw abroade, or deſcribe the greatneſſe of his lookes, the ſea ſhooke, the earth trembled, the hugie whales that wonted to ſporte vpon the rime of the water, durſt not then approch within a hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred fadom of the ſame, the heauens were threatned, and the whole earth ſhould be ſubdued. Then he beginneth with Englande, and goeth rounde about Scotland and Ireland, but Iehouah be pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, doing ſo little harme ſaue to himſelfe, that hee was not a little before ſo admired for his ſhape, great wordes, and bigge lookes, as nowe generally ſcorned for ſo ſmall perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance, after ſo many braue brags and threats, the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines birth prooued ſo ſéely a mouſe, that all feare was tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to laughter, and tremblings to ſhame for ſo doing. And I that ſaw the Monſter newly crept out of the ſhell, &amp; alſo in his greateſt pride, had ſcantly knowne him in the latter end of the yere 1588. (ſaue by his deformitie) ſo founde I him diſmembred, wounded, and humbled, beholding chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren that earſt durſt not looke him in the face, preſume in ſporte to plucke haires from his beard, and to daunce An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike on his great toe. No leſſe a change, me thought then to ſée a mouſe preſume to take a nappe in a Cattes eare. Then entred I into conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the power of him that indéede is onely mighty, and cried, ſaying: To thée O Lorde belongeth all glory, power, and honor, and vnto men, ſhame and confuſion: It is thou that throweſt the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:7102:9"/>proude euen to the duſt, exalting the humble and méeke in heart, to thée be all praiſe for euer.</p>
            <p>Now therefore hauing deſcribed him as I ſawe him in his pompe and fury, I thought good to picture him out in ſuch ſort as you ſée him in the beginning of the booke, being as lately he was ſéene by many: which may ſerue to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiue all ſuch daſtardes as were earſt well néere dead, at the onely hearing of his name, and for the comfort of all ſuch as ſtill truſted in God without wauering, that the great bugge at laſt would prooue but a very ſcare Crowe.</p>
            <p>I paſſing of late thorough a waſte and deſart wildernes, voyde of all gréene, and couered only with light ſande, ſtill remoouing at the pleaſure of the vnconſtant winde, by chance caſting my eye on one ſide I behelde (vnlooked for) many people of ſundry Nations gathered together, their confuſed noyſe being no leſſe ſtrange, then to ſée ſo deſert a place ſo repleniſhed with ſo many people, and to ridde my ſelfe of doubt I drewe néere, with deſire to be ſatiſfied of a matter ſo ſtraunge in reſpect of the place, where ſoone I beheld lying vnder a great branchles ſhrubbe, the great Monſter before rehearſed, and this great multitude inuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roning him round and gazing vpon him with their neuer ſatiſfied eyes: Some that expected he ſhould haue wrought great wonders, ſtoode pittifully howling ouer him, others that had long feared and ſomewhat felt the force of his fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, ſtoode giuing thankes to the almightie for ſo gratious a deliuerance: and others not caring which end of the ſtaffe went forwardes, (for there were of all ſortes) ſtoode laughing and grining and making mowes: which ſorte would haue béene as readie to runne with the hound, had the hound ſtill continued the chaſe, on hope to haue pykt the bones and fedde on the reuertion of the pray. This Monſters great heads that earſt ſpake great blaſphemies againſt heauen, lay now yéelding foorth againſt the ſame place (and him that ruleth therein) moſt bitter curſes, in the anguiſh of their diſtempered braynes, and with déepe and hollowe grones, bewrayed to all men their ſorrowes.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:7102:9"/>His right arme hanging downe the head, his crowne ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a one ſide, more after the falling then ſwearing faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, with the rich ſtone and pearle of his ſcabbard fallen off in many places, and his golden chape quite fallen off and loſt, yet there remayned many ſtones and pearles, with the golden hilt vppon the leaden blade, which blade at the firſt thruſt turned directly to his owne boſome, and being at the firſt drawen ſéemed ſo vnſutable to the rich ſcabbard that men wondred to ſée ſo braue a ſhew to couer ſo weake a weapon: his hautie ſpéech was altered from <hi>El mundo no me baſta,</hi> to his doubtfull demaund: <hi>No aprouechando Teſoro, que hare?</hi> Which in effect is thus much (if my treaſure auayle me not, what ſhall I doe?) (as though his infinite treaſure wherein he truſted, had quite decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued him): And therewith he ſet ſuch a ſigh, as pearced to the quicke euery entraile &amp; limme of the whole Monſter, in ſuch ſort as the whole body became ſo looſe with the feare, that it is doubted whether the laſke may be ſtopt till guts and all goe together into the préeuie: but in the meane time there was old ſtopping of noaſes, &amp; phogh quoth the beholders, what a ſtinking Holy-league is this? The left arme, that lately played ſuch Rex in France, beeing the very butcher of this League, vpon the Saintes of God, was now cleane cut from the body, by * one,
<note place="margin">The laſt fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch king who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing the purpoſe of this League, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Duke of Guize to be murthered.</note> who at the firſt ſate as newter till he ſaw that the Monſter in déed pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended in his ſayd progreſſe to bereaue him alſo of crowne &amp; life: then began <hi>Henry of Valoys</hi> to beſturre him, as one to whom a crowne &amp; life was more déere, then ſo to léeſe ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: and eſpying his time he layes ſo about him that eare euer the Monſter was ware, he ſmote the left arme quite off his ſhoulders, which in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fall brake his ſword, vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miting out with his blood, this frantick french <hi>Cruelle mort me preuient</hi> as much in engliſh as (Cruell death preuents me) meaning (as it ſéemes) that ſodaine death had preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his purpoſe, which reached euen to the kings own life, ſo that he gréeued more for not effectuating his purpoſe, then ſorrowed for conceiuing ſo great a ſinne in his heart.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:7102:10"/>
            <p>The bedye, bowelles, and other inwardes of the monſter, I ſawe ſo chaunged from that it was (lately deſcribed) that what with their <hi>vinum Theologicum</hi> and ouer ſoone exceſſe in ioy, but eſpecially their ſuddayne and vnexpected ſorrowe, euen when they thought all ſhould haue be'ene according to their longing, the whole ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach of the beaſt, was ſo ouercome, that his entrayles fell a ſending vpwarde, and his ſtomach ſpewing out ſuch blaſphemie againſt Heauen, and ſuch bitter curſes againſt the Church of Chriſt, that the ſtintch thereof was, and yet is ſtill aſcending into the noſtrelles of the Lorde: which ſtincke, though according to his long pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience he ſuffer for a ſeaſon, yet let not his Church diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payre, for at length when the ſtinch is at the greateſt, he will ſo deſtroy the whole bodie of this monſter, that not onely his curſſinges and blaſphemies ſhall ceaſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with his tyranny and power, but euerie lymme ſhall ſuddainely vaniſh away, as the whole bodie was at the firſt ouer haſtely begotten and hatcht into the worlde: But yet the number of Martyrs appoynted to ſuffer vnder Antichriſt is not full. Well, this late my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie bodie was againe of late ſo out of tune, and in ſo contrarie a note, that it made all the beholders much to maruaile, for in ſte'ede of <hi>(Neuer ſuch cauſe of ioy)</hi> (which was the ſpe'ech in the Monſters proſperitie) I heard playne mumbling amongeſt them <hi>(Neuer in like extremitie.)</hi> A ſoddayne chaunge, but what can not the Lorde bring to paſſe, howe can he'e turne the ioyes of the wicked into ſorrowe, and the croſſes of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into ſwe'ete eaſe: as this is the Lordes dooing, and it is woonderfull in our eyes.</p>
            <p>His twofolde tayle trayling after and contayning ſuch a number of people of all degre'es and ages, euen from Princes pe'eres, to the moſt abiectes people: the behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders alſo perceiued woonderfully altered: the one parte comming from the mothers head, were ſuch as were woonderfully bewitched by the charmes of the great Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cereſſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:7102:10"/>of Rome, and had quaffed de'epely out of her I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrous cuppe, whereby ſome of all ſortes became ſo ſuperſtitious, that they followed the League and Popes cauſe, of me'ere ſuperſtition onely: but theſe the ſimpleſt and ſmalleſt number: for the greateſt number were wholely of the Diuell the Syre, without any religion or deuotion at all, drawen onely by deſire of gayne and preferment, crying with the reſt, Oh the holy League, the holy League: yet they as careleſſe and voyde of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe and religion, as hee that neuer knewe the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of eyther: euen like the roagues, at the late defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of Lincolnes Inne, which neyther cared for Pren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes, nor had receiued any iniurie at the handes of anie Gentleman of the houſe, yet gladde of the leaſt oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie to robbe, ſpoyle and doe any miſchiefe what ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, had no thing in their mouthes, but, Oh the Pren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes, the Prentiſes, downe with the houſe, kill the raſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kalles, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Such, I ſay, were the greateſt followers of this League, hoping vppon the ſoddaine of vagabonds, and lubbars, to become Lordes at the firſt daſh, whereof, no doubt,
<note place="margin">In reſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ect of their wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full mixture, and that with the vildeſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions vnder heauen, as with the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gro, the Iewe &amp; the Moore, in ſuch ſort, that ſcant one among a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred can proue him ſelfe free from one of theſe three ſortes of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, eſpecially in Granada, Murc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a, Iaen, Andauzia, &amp;c,</note> they heard large promiſes made to all the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, which made the Spaniſh mungrelles, ſo haſtie to cauſe their Courtizans and Wiues to followe into Fraunce their inuincible Armada, promiſing againſt their comming hether to haue prouided for their enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynement, the fayreſt houſes in London, vaunting be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the victorie, to ſell veluets in Cheapeſide by the Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyer, and to meaſure out broade cloth by the pyke. But at length fayling of their purpoſe, and a cleane contrarie happe befalling their expectations: I ſawe there their heads in ſte'ede of helmets couered with coxecombes, and in ſte'ede of battleaxes, bables in their handes, ſo looking heauily one on another, none being able to mocke his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe for his long noaſe: I liſtning to their chatte, heard an Italian ſaying ſoftly to himſelfe, <hi>Cattiuo contare, ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al hoſto.</hi> Which I take to be thus in engliſh (ill recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:7102:11"/>without the hoaſt.</p>
            <p>The legges of this vgly ſhape, were as quite cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged as the reſt of the members: the young luſtie Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall on the one ſide, with the fatte fedde Biſhoppe on ſhe other, that earſt vpon hope ſéemed to daunce vnder the ponderous burthen, were now readie to ſinke right downe vnder the ſame, as not longer able (their hope loſt) to ſupport ſo great a waight: their ſhoulders were become crooked, and their eyes readie to ſtarte out of their heads, ſtaring as though they had béene ſitting thrée dayes and nightes at the Stillyeard cloſe by the Reniſh wine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fatte, their legges ſtoode trembling and quaking at the knées, as though they were euen readie to ſtart one part from the other: and the faynting Cardinall faynting in his ſpéech, in ſtéede of his former, vſed theſe wordes: <hi>ſpem &amp; laborem amitto,</hi> which I Engliſh thus (I léeſe both labour and hope). And the fatte mitred Biſhoppe, making a mouth like an Oyſter cryed out, <hi>Malè ſit one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri.</hi> As much to ſay (the Diuell take burthen and all) It ſhould ſéeme euerie Cardinall hopes to be Pope, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie ſuch Biſhoppe a Cardinall at leaſt, iuſtifying that ſaying, <hi>Nemo ſua ſorte contentus.</hi> Therefore it behoues all Cardinalles and ſuch Biſhoppes to laye to their hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping handes in time, eare they with the Popedome come all tumbling downe at once: And ſo they doe (ſay our Papiſtes) and though Pope Sirtus be dead, and ſo one of the Leagues heades be cut off, yet the Hydra neuer wanteth another to ſpring vppe in the place: And ſo it is moſt true, Pope Sixtus the fift is dead euen in the fifte yeare of his raygue, of whoſe death there goeth ſome doubt, ſome ſay that her Holineſſe was poyſoned, others that ſhe dyed euen of very griefe that her miſhapen Elfe had no better ſucceſſe in his enterpriſe, eyther of theſe apinions beare ſhewe of trueth, and it may be thought for moſt certaine, that one of theſe two cauſes was her death: but ſure, it is the Lordes dooing howe ſo euer it be, for he can vſe what meane hée thinketh beſt, when
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:7102:11"/>he thinketh good to remooue ſo cruell a ſcourge from his Church, we are not to hope for any much better but a worſe can not come out of Hell it ſelfe. Some ſay this newe Pope goeth about to bring foorth a newe League, others no, but that he will cure, refreſh and patch againe together the olde League: hoping that <hi>du Mayne</hi> and the Duke <hi>de Parma,</hi> will ſupply more amply the place of the olde Leagues leſt arme, both together, then the Duke of <hi>Guyze</hi> did alone: Once, old holde and kéepe there is and they that liue on the ſpoyle, crye out for a newn League out of hande, or that the olde may be repayred with all expedition: the Cloyſterers with the whole rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the Romiſh Clergie doubt greatly leaſt long delaye might bréede great daunger, and therefore theſe people prick the matter forward with no leſſe haſte the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their néed requireth ſpéede: but euery principall member of the olde League, finde themſelues at this inſtant ſo tyerde, that they deſire more a little preſent reſt, then a great hope of much eaſe hereafter.</p>
            <p>How ſo euer the matter falleth out, whether there bee a new League made or the olde renewed, let not the childe of God diſpayre or doubt, God is ſtill one and the ſame: no newe League can be made ſtronger, neyther the olde be renewed and made of greater force than the former: but could it be made a hundred times ſtronger, it is all one with God to ouercome with a great or ſmall number the greateſt hoaſt that euer was. Reioyce therefore O Sion for thy Redéemer liueth, and he that kéepeth Iſraell doeth neyther ſlumber nor ſléepe. Let the vniuerſall Church be ioyfull and ſing prayſes with one conſent, for Babell is falling, &amp; the mighty Giant that lately defyed heauen is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowen on earth, his bowe is broken and his ſpeare ſnapt a ſunder, his ioints are become féeble, &amp; the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die altogether out of temper: the Prince of glorie hath done it and the Lorde of Hoaſtes hath heard our prayers: the righteous God hath reuenged our wronges on the prow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of our foes, and declared to all the worlde how déere
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:7102:12"/>the bloud of his Saintes is alwayes in his ſight. And as he hath ouerthrowen the firſt, ſo let vs not doubt but he will doe the next.</p>
            <p>Bleſſed be his name for euer, and let all them that loue the peace of Ieruſalem ſay Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:7102:12"/>
            <head>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>VVIde ope thine eyes. O mighty king, at le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth begin to ſee, </l>
               <l>How heauens, how earth, do threat reuenge vnto thy realm &amp; thee</l>
               <l>Take pitty then on thee and thine, while mercy may be found:</l>
               <l>Before <hi>Iehouahs</hi> wrathfull face, fall flatte vnto the ground,</l>
               <l>Repent, returne, confeſſe and cry, for mercy at his hand.</l>
               <l>Whoſe members here on earth by thee, lye ſcattered on the land.</l>
               <l>Whoſe bloud, though ſcorcht on cruell flame, and ſhed by dint of ſword:</l>
               <l>Appeareth freſh before his face, that is both King and Lord:</l>
               <l>Of thee and all the earth beſides, for he hath made it all:</l>
               <l>He doth exalt the meeke in hart, the proud he maketh thrall:</l>
               <l>His eyes ſees all and he doth heare, the poore that are oppreſt,</l>
               <l>And eke the bloud that cries reuenge, and cals to be redreſt.
<note place="margin">Iulian the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour who of ſet purpoſe did ſtriue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Chriſt, and therefore greuouſly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted the Church, at le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth he find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome, hee threw duſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the aire, &amp; cryed, calling Chriſt Gallile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, thou Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lilean haſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed.</note>
               </l>
               <l>If ſtill thou ſtriue with him that ſtroue, (yet al againſt the ſtreame)</l>
               <l>Oercome with him, at length with him, thou alſo muſt proclaime.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thou Galilean haſt preuailde,</hi> for ſure he will preuaile,</l>
               <l>Gainſt all that dare reſiſt his power, or leaſt of his aſſaile.</l>
               <l>It is not thou, thy nature milde, is turnde to bitter gall.</l>
               <l>By them that rule (nay ouerrule) thy ſelfe, thy realme and all,</l>
               <l>With Pharaos witches they bewitch, thy ſences (mighty king)</l>
               <l>If ſtill thou liſt to what they ſay, thoſe witches will thee bring</l>
               <l>To fall with Pharao and his hoaſt, who warning none would take.</l>
               <l>Thy warnings are no leſſe then his, God grant they may thee make,</l>
               <l>Thy heauy hand to draw a backe, from all ſuch ſilly ſoules.</l>
               <l>That fly for feare of Tirants thine and hide themſelues in holes.</l>
               <l>Forſt leaue their lands and natiue ſoile, with infants young &amp; poore,</l>
               <l>To ſaue theyr throats &amp; fleſh from flame, they leeſe their goods &amp; ſtore:</l>
               <l>Retaine remorce (if ought be left) els ſeeke the ſame to haue.</l>
               <l>Relent to ſhed ſuch ſtore of bloud, which ſtil reuenge doth craue:</l>
               <l>It is not thou (as erſt I ſayd) thy witches worke our woe:</l>
               <l>Thy Inquiſition works thy wracke, and thou wilt finde it ſoe,</l>
               <l>They gape for bloud and wait for bloud, (yet all in hope of gaine)
<note place="margin">The Inquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hath the third part of euery man or woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s goods whom they condemne, &amp; the king the reſt, which makes the king as wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to ſuffer it, ast he blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Inquiſitors are ready to comdemn me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite, to the fire or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>llies.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Goods to conſiſcate to theyr vſe, their, credite to maintaine.</l>
               <l>They care not whome they racke or burne, ſo they may profite haue,</l>
               <l>So they may liue in wealth and pompe, what ſkils who go to graue,</l>
               <l>Or els to gallyes or to fire, their care is none at all.</l>
               <l>They ſpare no ſex nor age a lot, they nip both great and ſmall.</l>
               <l>Few nations of our Europe but, within thy Gallies rowes,</l>
               <l>With ſtore of ſtripes and iron chaines, of food ſmal ſtore God knowes,</l>
               <l>Saue onely bread and water thin, poore ſoules they haue no more,</l>
               <l>Within that Hell tereſtriall, theyr bodies euer ſore.</l>
               <l>With ſtripes on naked fleſh and bone, by tirants wretched hands,</l>
               <l>Whilſt that they row both day and night, faſt lockt in iron bands,</l>
               <l>Whereas the Turke more frendſhip findes, then chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poore diſtreſt,</l>
               <l>Of earthly aid and humane helpe, by torments ſtill oppreſt.</l>
               <l>There Engliſh men free borne and vnacquainted to be thrall,</l>
               <l>In time of trade, lees trade and goods, yea liberty and all.</l>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:7102:13"/>
               <l>For no cauſe els but that by chaunce,
<note place="margin">If an Engliſh reſtament or any booke of praier ſhould be found in a ſhippe, the whole com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with ſhip &amp; goods muſt fall into theyr bloudy hands, as wel as he that is owner of any ſuch booke. It is a wonder to ſee how without al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pitty thoſe cowards de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>orme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting pore chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtians that lye faſt bounde in chayns and howe they brag of theyr manhod in ſo doyng, as though they were conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, but were ſome of them looſe, that they ſo beate they woulde as ſoone bee bägd as once looke them in the face.</note> ſome booke there may be found,</l>
               <l>Abord ſome ſhip of holy write, or other doctrine ſound.</l>
               <l>For that offence (if ſo offence it well may termed bee)</l>
               <l>Both ſhip and goods and all the reſt, muſt pay as well as hee.</l>
               <l>That is the owner of the booke, he may not pay alone.</l>
               <l>He and his goods may not ſuffice, their harts more hard then ſtone,</l>
               <l>For all muſt to the holy Houſe, the beſt muſt needs be ſlaues.</l>
               <l>Their goods all loſt and freedome to, were better in their graues,</l>
               <l>And their thy cruel bloudy roags, that dare not ſtrike a dog,</l>
               <l>(That goeth looſe and ſtandeth free from iron chaine and clog)</l>
               <l>Lay load vpon our countrey men all naked and in bands,</l>
               <l>Sometime with ropes that ſmart full ſore, ſometime with hazel wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds</l>
               <l>And then they rule and <hi>dominier,</hi> like Princes for the time,</l>
               <l>They iet and looke as big perdy, as Bul beefe in the prime.</l>
               <l>Triumphing ouer chriſtian fleſh, like lion on his pray:</l>
               <l>Their luſt is law and what they do, there's none that ſaieth nay.</l>
               <l>Their pizels of their buls doe walke, more worſe then cut of ſworde,</l>
               <l>And ſaunce remorce they ſtill lay on, with many a bitter word.</l>
               <l>As raſcall, dog, and many ſuch, no chriſtian tongue would vtter:</l>
               <l>Againſt the image of our God, that may ne moue nor mutter.</l>
               <l>But heare and beare all what doth fall, from tirants tongue &amp; arme.</l>
               <l>If any ſpeake, they ſoone prouide, to ſtop his ſpeech a charme.</l>
               <l>They hale his tongue out of his mouth, and take a clouen ſticke.</l>
               <l>Twixt which they binde the tender tongue, (a cruell helliſh tricke)</l>
               <l>For ſo they make him row and hale, enduring thirſt and paine,</l>
               <l>In torments drawing forth his liſe, that dead would be ful faine.</l>
               <l>The moiſture of his mouth in ropes, hangs downe on fainting breſt,</l>
               <l>His ſon-tand hide not free the while, but ſtill with ſtrokes oppreſt.</l>
               <l>His ſweat and tears ſtil trickling downe, with drops of bloud among,</l>
               <l>Doth ſeeme to plead forpitty and, releaſe of open wrong,</l>
               <l>But no releaſe nor yet remorce, but rather bitter ſkornes,</l>
               <l>Poore ſoules they ſinde in ſteede of eaſe, nought els but pricking thorns</l>
               <l>Then at the length when as thee ſee, the ſilly ſoule to ſinke:</l>
               <l>And faint in thirſt and ſorrow ſuch, as greeueth me to thinke.</l>
               <l>They eftſoones free his fettered tongue, ſo ſwollen with the paine:</l>
               <l>That ſcarce the mouth with much a doe, receaues the ſame againe.</l>
               <l>This is the food, this is the fare, and lodging like the reſt</l>
               <l>Or foode and raiment haue our men, that are to Gallies preſt.</l>
               <l>The Holy houſe (vnholy rather) a houſe of vgly ſinne,</l>
               <l>The Gallies next, both earthly Hels, to ſuch as enter in,</l>
               <l>I thinke their peeres or els their likes, are no where to be found,</l>
               <l>VVithin our Europe (well I know) nor ſearce aboue the ground.</l>
               <l>Nor yet in Hell, becauſe that there, the wicked men alone,</l>
               <l>And ſuch ne feare ne know the Lorde, in torments make their mone,</l>
               <l>But in thoſe Spaniſh Hels the good, and bad endure like woe,</l>
               <l>Homicides, roges, theeues and Turkes, with good are plagued ſo:</l>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:7102:13"/>
               <l>There good and bad do ſinart alike, ſmall choiſe is made of either,</l>
               <l>They lay on ſtill on euery ſide, and ſtrike they care not whether.</l>
               <l>And in the holy houſe the good, are ſtill tormented more.</l>
               <l>Then Sodomits, or he that hath, three wiues at once in ſtore,
<note place="margin">They preferre Sodomites &amp; dogs before vs, ſuch is the charity of the hollieſt place in all Spayne, as themſelues ſay, what then t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e charity of al the reſt of Spain may be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> refer me to your iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>
               </l>
               <l>For theſe are things that do belong, to Iudgement of that place.</l>
               <l>As well as our religion (though not in ſuch diſgrace)</l>
               <l>For why, the filthy Sodomite, and vildeſt wretch that is.</l>
               <l>Before vs far they do prefer, and yet more worſe then this.</l>
               <l>They terme vs dogs, yea them prefer, before the beſt of vs,</l>
               <l>Few men would thinke (who know it not) that we are vſed thus.</l>
               <l>But thus and worſe, yea far more worſe, then I can write or ſay.</l>
               <l>They vs torment with torments ſuch, as doth vs dayly ſlay.</l>
               <l>The feare and griefe of which doth make, full many a man confeſſe,</l>
               <l>The word or deede he neuer did, or hardly thought much leſſe,</l>
               <l>But once confeſſe, they haue their wils, and may do what they pleaſe,</l>
               <l>Our ſobs, their ſmiles, our grief their gain, our torments are their eaſe</l>
               <l>Theſe things agree not with thy kinde, (O king) they are to baſe.</l>
               <l>For ſon of mightie Charles that, did laſt poſſeſſe thy place,</l>
               <l>He wold not ſo haue gotten golde, nor made of bloud a gaine.</l>
               <l>Nor rakte vp treaſure to himſelfe, ſo much to good mens paine.</l>
               <l>He would haue ſuffered ſuch abuſe, if he had liued long</l>
               <l>Nor yet permitted Baals prieſts; to do ſuch open wrong,</l>
               <l>He would haue warred on the Turks; and made the More to bow:</l>
               <l>And not imbroode in chriſtian blood his hands, as thou doeſt now:</l>
               <l>what erſt was won perforce from Turke, again thou haſt it loſt.
<note place="margin">That which Charles and others won &amp; kept in Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bary from the Turke, thys king hath loſt through the great deſire he hath to make wars in chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Still warring where thou ſhouldeſt aide, and that with inickle coſt.</l>
               <l>And ſith that God hath ſeated thee, to weare his crown in Spaine.</l>
               <l>To yeelde accompt to God of this, thou ſurely ſhalt be faine.</l>
               <l>For what thy tirants do, thou doeſt, ſith thou doeſt giue them leaue,</l>
               <l>And if thou looke not well in time, they alſo will bereaue,</l>
               <l>Thee of thy earthly crowne and rule, for that they bring in hate.</l>
               <l>To all the world both thee and thine, with all thy roiall ſtate.</l>
               <l>For all who erſt haue wronged beene, &amp; ſuch whoſe friends had wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g.</l>
               <l>Do call reuenge and threat reuenge, with hope ere it be long.</l>
               <l>(If thou do not relent in time) for to performe it ſo,</l>
               <l>That thou with them and they with thee, will find it to your woe.</l>
               <l>Tis vaine to truſt too much in golde, or <hi>Indias</hi> ſiluer mines,</l>
               <l>Or els to friends that are but friends, ſo long as Fortune ſhines.</l>
               <l>And ſeemes to lull thee in her lap, but bend ſhee once her brow.</l>
               <l>Thy friends are gone ere thou beware, or ſcarſely knoweſt how,</l>
               <l>For friendſhip forſt doth wauer ſtill, and waiteth but a time,</l>
               <l>For to reuolt, though biding yet, till things grow more in prime.</l>
               <l>All are not friends that are thy thrall, perforce gainſt right and will.</l>
               <l>VVhat ſhew ſoeuer they do make, their hate remaineth ſtill.</l>
               <l>And ſtill doe hope but for a day, to ſet their ſhoulders free.</l>
               <l>From ſeruile yoke and tirants fell, appointed ſo by thee.</l>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:7102:14"/>
               <l>To rule and raigne and bear a ſway, to murther and to ſpoſle,</l>
               <l>Such as are vnder thy hard hand, in any forraine ſoile:</l>
               <l>Sure God the righter of all wronges, doth limit time and age.</l>
               <l>How long all tirants ſhall remaine, and rule in bloudy rage,</l>
               <l>VVhich time and age no man ſhall paſſe, no, not a moment ſmall.</l>
               <l>But at the time that God appoints,
<note place="margin">King Charles the laſt of: that name, that conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed to the maſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſacre, died bleeding at the noſe, eyes, mouth, and al other vents in the body. The laſt king, and brother to Charles, being young, was by the Guiſes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eurement, a chiefe actor in the maſſas cre, with D. of Guiſes, was the firſt that altered his na ture to make him take ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſare in the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of bloud, and therefore by the iuſt indge ment of God he cauſed the Guiſe to be murthered, ſo ſo daynly, that he had no time to repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</note> perforce they periſh all.</l>
               <l>Let Charles of France, be in thy minde, who did but yeelde conſent</l>
               <l>Vnto that ſlaughter in his Realme, whereof he did repent,</l>
               <l>Yet by his death the Lord would ſhew, his wrath in ſome degree.</l>
               <l>His vents all bleeding till his corps, of life and bloud was free.</l>
               <l>But the cheefe authors of the fact, though yet they liued long,</l>
               <l>In time receaude their due deſert, and recompence of wrong.</l>
               <l>Firſt, <hi>Guyes</hi> that great bloud thirſty beaſt, and auctor of that ill:</l>
               <l>Which neuer ſeemde to be ſuffiſde, or haue of bloud his fill.</l>
               <l>The Lord appointed at the length, when now his ſin was ripe,</l>
               <l>And growen vp vnto the full,, that he ſhould haue his ſtripe,</l>
               <l>By his appointment, whome he taught and firſt inuerd to bloud,</l>
               <l>He of himſelfe not being ſo, his nature was more good,</l>
               <l>For by the <hi>Guyſe</hi> he was induſte, to do what ſo he did,</l>
               <l>And was partaker of his ſinne, that els would not haue ſlidde.</l>
               <l>Therefore the Lord appointed ſo, within his ſecret deeme,</l>
               <l>That he alone ſhould be the man, to ſend him to his toome.</l>
               <l>Without regard of friendſhip paſt, the <hi>Guyſe</hi> doth ſeeke his death,</l>
               <l>The king it knowes which to pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uent, he ſtops the <hi>Guyſes</hi> breath,</l>
               <l>So makes him wallow in his geare, that erſt had ſhed ſo much</l>
               <l>Of other mens without remorce, and now his death is ſuch.</l>
               <l>Euen like the man that taught his crow, to eat and pull out eyes,</l>
               <l>Of Lambes and other ſimple beaſts, her huuger to ſuffice,</l>
               <l>The Crow inured ſtill thereto, ere that the man it wiſte,</l>
               <l>Shee pluckt an eie out of his head, while ſitting on his fifte.</l>
               <l>Such are the iudgements of our God, and ſo he brings about,</l>
               <l>The ſcholler in ſuch vgly ſinne, doth roote the maiſter out.</l>
               <l>But Iuſtice yet not fully done, though king repent the deede,</l>
               <l>The Lord will ſurely be reuengde, and make all ſuch to bleede,</l>
               <l>As ſhed the bloud of Innocents, and do his ſaints ſuch harme.</l>
               <l>His power is naught at all abridgd, ne ſhortened is his arme,</l>
               <l>And who hath he reſernde in ſtore to touch the Lords annoine:
<note place="margin">Noate.</note>
               </l>
               <l>To dare lay hands vppon the king, to ioypard ſuch a ioynt.</l>
               <l>Euen they aduanced by him moſt, and whom he loued beſt,</l>
               <l>And of all the other hypocrites, prefer before the reſt,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Iacobins,</hi> euen thoſe the Lord appointed for the fact,</l>
               <l>To lay their hands vppon the king,
<note place="margin">The Iacobins are an order of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>vers, whom the king moſte preſerred.</note> they did that bloudy act.</l>
               <l>O depth vnſercht and ſecrets ſuch, as neuer may be knowen,</l>
               <l>By humane wit, till thou (O Lord) vouchſafe to haue it ſhowen,</l>
               <l>In time, decreede by thy ſelfe, then all the world ſhall ſee.</l>
               <l>Thy holy Iudgements what they are, and what thy counſails bee.</l>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:7102:14"/>
               <l>But what, ſhall that vngrations houſe, that durſt to be ſo bold,</l>
               <l>To lay their hands vpon their King, eſcape ſo vncontrold?</l>
               <l>No ſure, I know they all ſhall rue, that vile and curſed deed,</l>
               <l>Ere it be long, as they deſerue, I hope to ſee them ſpeed:</l>
               <l>As of the reſt none haue eſcapte, that were the chiefe of al,</l>
               <l>In the maſſacre done in France, vpon both great and ſmal:</l>
               <l>So ſure the rods that whipped them, at length muſt into ſire,</l>
               <l>They were but great Iehouahs whips, I meane the curſed frire</l>
               <l>With all his crue that did conſent, vnto King <hi>Henries</hi> death,</l>
               <l>Agreeing ſo amongſt themſelues, as beaſts deuoyd of faith.</l>
               <l>Bethinke thee well (O King) of this, and trie where thou be cleere,</l>
               <l>And innocent of ſuch offence, as is rehearſed heere.</l>
               <l>Flying fame doth ſay, if ſhe ſay true, that <hi>Orange</hi> Prince was ſlaine</l>
               <l>By thee alone, ſith thou alone, didſt promiſe largely gaine,</l>
               <l>To him that ſhould commit the fact, which, gaine did bring to paſſe:</l>
               <l>A Spaniard tooke the ſame in hand, moſt like a wilfull Aſſe,</l>
               <l>And did performe it villanouſly, who after had his hire,</l>
               <l>Not of thy gold, but cruell death, as iuſtice did require.</l>
               <l>Fame ſaith more, that thou art ſtainde, in death of proper ſonne:</l>
               <l>Thinke ſure to yeelde accompt of all, what euer thou haſt done:</l>
               <l>For many things are bruted more, which I dare not reporte,</l>
               <l>The Lord doth knowe them euery one, both where, and in what ſorte,</l>
               <l>And where thou ſhouldeſt aide ſuch kings, whoſe ſubiects do rebell,</l>
               <l>How thou it doſt, this Realme and France, may witnes very well:</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſubiects neuer woulde haue ſturde, but by thy proſſerd aide,</l>
               <l>Of men and money in their need, which makes them not afraide</l>
               <l>Of God, nor Prince, nor of the Law, that bids vs all obay</l>
               <l>Our Prince appointed by the Lord, the ſcepter for to ſway,</l>
               <l>But daily riſe, and doe rebell, and all on hope of thee,</l>
               <l>Againſt their Prince protect by God, that doth thy ſhifting ſee,</l>
               <l>And will reward thee for the ſame, be ſure, ſome way or other,</l>
               <l>What is deferd, is not forgote, nor yet forgiuen neither.</l>
               <l>What doeſt thou elſe, in doing thus, then teach thy ſubiects plaine.</l>
               <l>How to rebell againſt thy ſelfe, and driue thee out of Spaine.</l>
               <l>What meaſure that thou meat, ſaith Chriſt, look for the ſame again:</l>
               <l>It doth but blot thy fame, O King, and bring thy name in hate:</l>
               <l>Both thou and thine are nowe abhorde, in euery ciuill ſtate,</l>
               <l>Saue mongſt the Papiſts of this Realme, and rebels vp in France,</l>
               <l>They onely loue thee for thy golde, on hope thou wilt aduance,</l>
               <l>And them preferre to high eſtate, when thou haſt conquerd all:</l>
               <l>They knowe thy purpoſe and thy drift, and ſo obey thy call.</l>
               <l>But if thou ſtill proceede in that, wherein thou art begunne,</l>
               <l>And go on ſtill to weaue the webbe, that hypocrites haueſpunne.</l>
               <l>Then marke the end, nay feare the end, yea feare thy finall fall,</l>
               <l>Not onely vnto thee and thine, but to thy Realines and all.</l>
               <l>Thy wealth doth make thee cleane forget, both God, &amp; what thou art.</l>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:7102:15"/>
               <l>As did that mighty Babell king, till that he felt the ſmarte,</l>
               <l>Of feeding in the fields with beaſts, and felt the clowdy raine</l>
               <l>Diſtill, vpon his vnclad backe, with other bitter paine:</l>
               <l>Then in his griefe he knew the Lord, that would not in his wealth</l>
               <l>So ſure thy gold doth blind thine eies, from ſeeking of thy health</l>
               <l>At his good hands that giues thee gold, and makes thee ſo abound</l>
               <l>In treaſure, more then any prince, that liueth on the ground:</l>
               <l>But to an other vſe then yet, thou doeſt the ſame beſtow,</l>
               <l>He giues thee golde that erſt was hid within the earth below:</l>
               <l>For thou employeſt it to moleſt, none but the Chriſtian poore:</l>
               <l>While crauing truce with cruel Turk, to ſcourge our Chr. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more,</l>
               <l>Thou leav'ſt the Turk to liue at eaſe, &amp; laugh at chriſtian harms,</l>
               <l>While he fits frce, poore Europe is, by thee al vp in armes:</l>
               <l>By thee (O King) and by the Pope, that man and childe of ſin,</l>
               <l>Which addeth oyle vnto the flame, yea poureth ſtore therein:</l>
               <l>Nay, he is all in all we knowe, and makes thee but his meane,</l>
               <l>To mowe and cut the harueſt downe, that he againe may gleane,</l>
               <l>And gather all the croppe himſelfe, and laugh thee but to ſcorne,</l>
               <l>When thou haſt ſpent thy wealth &amp; ſweat, and he poſſeſt the corne.</l>
               <l>Looke well in time, for this is true, withdraw thy hand abacke</l>
               <l>Before it be too late, and ſo, thou wholy go to wracke:</l>
               <l>For Europe longer will not beare the loade thou layeſt on,</l>
               <l>Nor yet abide ſuch torments as, thou layeſt thy thralles vpon.</l>
               <l>All chriſtian princes ſmell thy drifts, and ſee thy haught aſpire,</l>
               <l>Thy *<hi>vbi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                     <note place="margin">Theſe are the vaine and prowd poſies of the king of Spaine.</note> regnabo</hi> and the reſt, thou prowdly doeſt require,</l>
               <l>Thy *<hi>non ſufficit orbis,</hi> which bewrays whereto thy hart is bente</l>
               <l>when notwithſtanding at the length, thy feeble corps once pent</l>
               <l>And cloſe ſhut vp in compas of ſix foote, or thereabout,</l>
               <l>That little ſtraight muſt thee ſuffice, ſaus any ſally out,</l>
               <l>Till when the trumpet ſhrill thee warne, with euery other wight,</l>
               <l>To riſe, to go, to giue accompt, before that Iudges ſight,</l>
               <l>Which onely iudgeth iuſtly ſtill, and will reward eachone</l>
               <l>According to his faith and fruits: for Chriſt is Iudge alone,</l>
               <l>That knows the ſecrets of al harts,
<note place="margin">The fruites of faith are the good workes which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede from ſaith.</note> &amp; what our works haue beene,</l>
               <l>Then good, ſhall good reward receiue, and wicked ſuffer teene.</l>
               <l>Gold then and droſſe of like accompt, then ſcepter beareth ſway</l>
               <l>No more then Shepheards crabtree crooke, in that great dreadful day,</l>
               <l>Thy India mines, wherewith (as now) thou vndermineſt all,</l>
               <l>And dayly doſt ſubuert the ſtate, of chriſtian Kings withall,</l>
               <l>Will be of none effect (as then) where Iudge is vncorrupt,</l>
               <l>And that he ſhould not iuſtly iudge, who dares him interrupt:</l>
               <l>There is no power but onely his, all fleſh ſhall quaking ſtand,</l>
               <l>Then King and beggar both alike,
<note place="margin">The Licences that the pope felles to finne, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> not the fits to his cheſts, for there is no ſin ſo hainous but eyther a man may b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e a licence to commit it, or a pardon for the ſame after it is commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: and it is not to be dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted but that the king of Spaine payde well for his licence, for his laſt ince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuous mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage. Not onely his friendes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay, but his wealth waſtes like buttar a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſun, by paying penſions to traitors, and buying that for money of corrupt cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines which he dares not attempt to winne by va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoode, for his conqueſts conſiſt more in coyne then in ſteele: and parte of his Fleete that were wont to go home ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, fall nowe and then ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the bottome, or into their hands that ſpend it as me rily as he would em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy it mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily.</note> muſt holde vp guiltie hand.</l>
               <l>Then Pope that pardons others now, and licence ſelles to ſin,</l>
               <l>Shall pardon ſeeke, but none ſhall finde, nor be admitted in</l>
               <l>The golden gates of Sion ſweet, whereof to haue the keies</l>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:7102:15"/>
               <l>The caytife brags and boaſts abroad, as lord of land and ſeas</l>
               <l>To haue ſupreame authoutie, of heauen gates and hell,</l>
               <l>And whom he liſts in either place, to put for aye to dwell.</l>
               <l>O beaſt, aie kicking gainſt the pricke, how long wilt thou prouoke</l>
               <l>Our good long-patient righteous God, that iuſtly might thee choke,</l>
               <l>And ſtop thy moſt blaſphemous throat, with vengeance in his ire,</l>
               <l>yet ſtill forbeares and lets thee liue, to worke thy whole deſire,</l>
               <l>Vpon his church and ſaints on earth, till that thy time be full:</l>
               <l>And then his wrath, yea all at once, ſhall light vpon thy ſcull.</l>
               <l>Then ſhall thoſe kings and mighty men, whom thou bewitcheſt ſo,</l>
               <l>Prouoking them to be thy whippes, aye working Chriſtians woe:</l>
               <l>Euen they ſhall hate thee in extreame, whom now they loue ſo much,</l>
               <l>And eate thy fleſh (thou filthy whoore) their hatred will be ſuch:</l>
               <l>And all the nations of the earth, ſhall wonder at thy fall,</l>
               <l>And at the mighty Citty who ſo ſwayeth ouer all:</l>
               <l>For both at once, both it and thou, ſhall quite be ouerthrowen,</l>
               <l>In that ſame houre, which to the Lord, as yet is onely knowen:</l>
               <l>Then ſhall the church of Chriſt reioyce, and crie with perfect ioy,</l>
               <l>The City and hir Queene are fallen, that wrought vs ſuch annoy,</l>
               <l>Yea ſure the time is hard at hand, one king alone remains</l>
               <l>For to vpholde thy waining ſtate, vnto his coſt and paines:</l>
               <l>And he was neuer ſeene ſo weake, his friends ſtill ſliding backe,</l>
               <l>Maintaine him well, for he once gone, then comes thy totall wracke,</l>
               <l>Who knowes howe ſoone he may be gone? or whether that the Lord</l>
               <l>Vouchſafe him mercy at the length, and ſo of ſelfe accorde</l>
               <l>Reiect thee quite, and hate thee more, then euer lou'd before:</l>
               <l>The Lord, be ſure (if ſo he pleaſe) can do a great deale more.</l>
               <l>Thy kingdome whilom ſeated was, on many more then hee,</l>
               <l>When greateſt part of Chriſtendome, paid tribute vnto thee,</l>
               <l>Now Spaine alone is all thy prop, forſakde of other Kings,</l>
               <l>And he alone doth grone to beare, himſelfe ſuch heauy things,</l>
               <l>As made ſo many ſtoupe before, muſt needs now make him bend,</l>
               <l>As weary to ſupport thy waight, or longer thee defend,</l>
               <l>The time, no doubt, draws on apace, that all thy pomp muſt end.</l>
               <l>Meane while bethinke thee (king of Spaine) &amp; ſhake thy burden off,</l>
               <l>Ere vnder loade thou lie adowne, and ſo remaine a ſcoffe</l>
               <l>To all the world, becauſe forwarnde, thou haſt vin ſundry times,</l>
               <l>Both of the burden and the man, wyth all his filthy crimes.</l>
               <l>Thou art not wiſer then the reſt, of all our Europe kings,</l>
               <l>That ſo do hate the ſhameleſſe whore, that naught but horror brings</l>
               <l>To all the earth as well is ſeene, by bloud ſo dayly ſhead,</l>
               <l>And by the wars which for his ſake, ore Chriſtendome is ſpread.</l>
               <l>If thou continue him to aide, with him thou needs muſt fall:</l>
               <l>For prince and people that him ſerue, with him muſt periſh all:</l>
               <l>Els ſhould the Scripture be vntrue, which neuer man ſhall proue,</l>
               <l>For heauen and earth ſhal paſſe away, with ſtarres and things aboue,</l>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:7102:16"/>
               <l>But not a lot or any word of Scripture, ſhall ſo paſſe,</l>
               <l>But ſtill remaine in perfect force, as ſtrong as euer it was.</l>
               <l>God graunt thee grace as he hath done, already to the reſt,</l>
               <l>Of Europe Kings that now do liue, by great Iehouah bleſt:</l>
               <l>Who bleſſe thee too, and turne thy heart, that thou maiſt make vp one</l>
               <l>And ſo be numbred with the beſt, and leaue the Pope alone:</l>
               <l>Whoſe portion ſhall be with the dogges, and hypocrites without,</l>
               <l>That haue their pleaſures in this world, and liue ſans feare &amp; doubt.</l>
               <l>Bleſſe ſtill, good Lord, our Queene, &amp; Realme, &amp; grant thy ſeruant long</l>
               <l>Ore vs to raigne within this Realme, protect hir from all wrong,</l>
               <l>Of Pope and other bloodie foes, that ſeeke hir bloud to ſpill:</l>
               <l>Confound them all that ſo conſpire, and barre them of their will.</l>
               <l>Forget not *<hi>Henry</hi> ſore oppreſt,
<note place="margin">The French King.</note> by ſubiects fell vnkinde:</l>
               <l>Euen as thou haſt annointed him, ſo haue him ſtill in minde:</l>
               <l>The great fat bulles of Baſan ſtill, do compaſſe him about:</l>
               <l>They neuer ceaſe him to purſue, and all to roote him out,</l>
               <l>From thence, where thou haſt placed him, a King by thee to raigne:</l>
               <l>Subdue their rage, and let him rule, to their deſpite and paine:</l>
               <l>Let neuer fleſh preſume to ſtriue, againſt thy mightie will:</l>
               <l>But let them fall amidſt their pride, and be confounded ſtill:</l>
               <l>Leaſt fleſhe in pride do boaſt abroad, and ſay, who is the Lord,</l>
               <l>Who is the God on whom they reſt? wher is his mighty ſword?</l>
               <l>That ſometimes ſlew, ſuch as withſtood, king Dauid and the reſt,</l>
               <l>Of Iſraels kings. So let them die, that hate, whom thou haſt bleſt.</l>
               <l>Thou haſt good Lord appointed him, in Fraunce to rule by thee.</l>
               <l>Let noue reſiſt thy will good God, and from thy wrath go free,</l>
               <l>Let Parina with his Spaniſh rout, that ſo the king moleſt.</l>
               <l>Feele all thy heauy wrath on him, with his and all the reſt.</l>
               <l>That ſo rebell againſt their king, let none eſcape thy hand.</l>
               <l>But let them be before the winde, as chaff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vppon the lanb.</l>
               <l>And let the king rule ſtill in peace, in ſpite of whom ſayes nay.</l>
               <l>Lord heare thy Church in time of neede, turne not thy face away.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:7102:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
